<page>

<h1>Example 2: tidying up example 1</h1>
 
<p>
    This models is the same as in example 1, except that the definitions have been split out into several self-contained 
    files. The files can be downloaded together as <a href="examples.zip">examples.zip</a>.
</p> 
<p>
    The main file, included below, uses the <x>Include</x> element to include definitions from other files. Each file 
    is only read once, even if several files include it. Because some of these files, such as the HH channel definitions,
    are intended to be used on their own, they include all the dimension definitions they need. These may also occur 
    in other files with the same dimension names. This is fine as long as the dimensions being declared are the same.
    An error will be reported if a new definition is supplied that changes any of the values. The same applies 
    for <x>Unit</x> definitions. For other element types names and ids must be unique. An id or name can't appear twice, even
    if the content of the elements is the same.
</p>

<h2>The main model</h2>

<p>
    This defines a few components, then a network that uses them and a simulation to run it all. The HHCell component
    refers to channel types coming from the included hhmodels.xml file which in turn depends on hhcell.xml and hhchannel.xml.
</p>

<xinclude src="../../examples/example2.xml"/>


<h2>Included files</h2>

<xinclude src="../../examples/ex2dims.xml"/>


<p>
    The file hhchannel.xml contains complete definitions of a fairly general HH-style channel model with any number 
    of gates based on the three standard types used in the original HH work.
</p>

<xinclude src="../../examples/hhchannel.xml"/>


<p>
As mentioned in example1, the numerics are too feeble to cope with this gate definition though, so a change of 
variables is employed instead:
</p>
<xinclude src="../../examples/hhaltgate.xml"/>

<p>
    The file hhcell.xml defines a simple cell model with some populations of HH channels.
</p>

<xinclude src="../../examples/hhcell.xml"/>

<p>
A couple of spike generators.
</p>

<xinclude src="../../examples/spikegenerators.xml"/>

<p>
And now the components themselves. These are the standard HH sodium and potassium channels (as used in Rallpack3).
</p>
<xinclude src="../../examples/hhmodels.xml"/>

<p>
Some miscellaneous iaf models.
</p>

<xinclude src="../../examples/misciaf.xml"/>

<p>
Finally, a small collection of dimension definitions useful for things like the miscellaneous iaf cell definitions.
</p>

<xinclude src="../../examples/elecdims.xml"/>

</page>