<page title="LEMS - Low Entropy Model Specification">


<h1>LEMS: Low Entropy Model Specification</h1>
 <h2 class="sub">A language for specifying hierarchical models based on fundamental physical relationships</h2>


 <p class="version">Current version: <versioninfo/>  &#160;&#160; <a href="lems.pdf">These pages as a single PDF</a></p>	
   
   
   <p>
   	LEMS is being developed to provide a compact, minimally redundant, human-readable,
   	human-writable, declarative way of expressing models of biological systems. 
   </p>
   <p>
   	It differs from other systems such as CellML or SBML in its requirement to be human writable
   	and the inclusion of basic physical concepts such as dimensionality and physical nesting as 
   	part of the language.
   </p>

   <p>
   	The main goal is to enable model developers to write declarative models in LEMS in
   	much the same way as software developers write software applications in computer languages 
   	such as in C, Java or Python. 
   </p>
   
      <p>
   	The examples shown here use XML for expressing models as text, but LEMS is not 
   	primarily an XML language. Rather it defines a set of structures for representing
   	models. The reference implementation also supports a more concise indentation-based
   	format for representing models.
   </p>
   
   <p>
   	There are two independent implementaitons of LEMS: jLEMS, written in Java 
   	and pyLEMS written in Python. Both are hosted on the <a href="http://github.com/LEMS">github.com/LEMS</a>.
   </p>

   <p>
   	LEMS forms an essential part of <b>NeuroML version 2.0</b> See <a href="https://docs.neuroml.org/Userdocs/NeuroMLv2.html#defining-dynamics-in-lems">here</a> for more details.
   </p>
   
   
   <h2>Contents</h2>
 <p>
 <ul>
 <li>A <a href="introduction.html">An overview</a> of how types and models are declared</li>
    <li>A <a href="elements.html">The elements available</a> for defining and using user-defined types</li>
  
       <li>Some examples (left menu)
      illustrating how elements can be defined and used.</li>     
    <li>A brief <a href="discussion">discussion</a> of the objectives, design issues, benefits and weaknesses of this approach</li>
     
 </ul>
 </p>
 
 <p>
    The best place to start is probably the <a href="example1.html">first example</a>. Anyone familiar with modeling and 
    model specification should be able to read the XML and make out what is going on.  
 </p>
 
 
  
 <h2>Capabilities</h2>
 
 <p>
    You can define <x>ComponentType</x>s (e.g. a "HH channel" or "a bi-exponential synapse") which express the general
    properties of a particular type of thing that goes in a model. This includes saying what parameters they have, what 
    child elements they are allowed, and how they behave (the equations).
 </p>
 <p>
    You can then define <x>Component</x>s based on these types by supplying values for the parameters and adding any child elements
    that are required, so, for example, a bi-exponential synapse model with rise time 1ms and decay 5ms would be a component.
 </p>
 <p><x>ComponentType</x>s can extend other <x>ComponentType</x>s to add extra parameters, fix certain values, and otherwise
 modify their behavior. <x>Component</x>s can extend other <x>Component</x>s to reuse specified parameter values.
 There is also a loose notion of abstract types, so a component can accept children with a particular lineage
 without needing to know exactly what type they are. This can be used, for example, to define cells that accept 
 synaptic connections provided they have a particular signature.
 </p>
 
 <p>Each <x>ComponentType</x> can have a <x>Dynamics</x> element that specifies how it behaves: what the state variables are, the equations
 that govern them, and what happens when events are sent or received. 
    The interpreter takes a model consisting of type and component elements referenced from a network, builds an instance
    from them and runs it.
 </p>
 
 <p>
    For those familiar with object oriented languages, the <x>ComponentType</x>/<x>Component</x> distinction is close to the normal
    Class/Instance distinction. When the model is run, the same pattern applies again, with the <x>Component</x>s acting
    as class definitions, with their "instances" actually containing the state variables in the running mode.
 </p>
 
 
 <h2>Background</h2>
 <p>
    The <a href="http://www.neuroml.org/files/NeuroMLWorkshop2010.pdf">March 2010 NeuroML meeting</a> identified a need to extend the capability within NeuroML for expressing a range
    of models of synapses. It was decided that the hitherto adopted approach of defining parameterized building blocks to 
    construct models by combining blocks and setting parameters was unlikely to be flexible enough to cope with the needs 
    for synapse models. This is not obvious a-priori, since, for example, the pre NeuroML 2.0 ion channel
    building blocks are fully adequate to describe the dynamics of a wide range existing channel models. But there appears to be
     no such commonality in models used for synapses, where the mechanisms used range from highly detailed biochemical
    models to much more abstract ones.
 </p>
   
 
    <p>
        This work also has antecedents in Catacomb 3, which was essentially a GUI for a component definition system and 
        model builder using a type system similar to that proposed here. Much of the XML processing code used in the interpreter
        was taken from <a href="http://www.neuroml.org/tool_support.php#PSICS">PSICS</a> which itself currently uses the "building block" approach to model specification.
        The need for user-defined types has been considered with respect to future PSICS development, and this proposal also
        reflects potential requirements for PSICS.
 </p>
 
 <h2>Example</h2>
 
 <p>
 Here is the XML for a simple integrate-and-fire cell definition:
 <xcode>
     <ComponentType name="refractiaf">
         <Parameter name="threshold" dimension="voltage"/>
         <Parameter name="refractoryPeriod" dimension="time"/>
         <Parameter name="capacitance" dimension="capacitance"/>
         <Parameter name="vleak" dimension="voltage"/>
         <Parameter name="gleak" dimension="conductance"/>

         <Parameter name="current" dimension="current"/>
         <Parameter name="vreset" dimension="voltage"/>
         <Parameter name="deltaV" dimension="voltage"/>
         <Parameter name="v0" dimension="voltage"/>

         <EventPort name="out" direction="out"/>
         <EventPort name="in" direction="in"/>

         <Exposure name="v" dimension="voltage"/>

         <Dynamics>
             <StateVariable name="v" exposure="v" dimension="voltage" />   
             <StateVariable name="tin" dimension="time"/>
             <OnStart>
                 <StateAssignment variable="v" value="v0"/>
             </OnStart>

             <Regime name="refr">
                 <OnEntry>
                     <StateAssignment variable="tin" value="t" />
                     <StateAssignment variable="v" value="vreset" />
                 </OnEntry>
                 <OnCondition test="t .gt. tin + refractoryPeriod">
                     <Transition regime="int" />
                 </OnCondition>
             </Regime>

             <Regime name="int" initial="true">
                 <TimeDerivative variable="v" value="(current + gleak * (vleak - v)) / capacitance" />
                 <OnCondition test="v .gt. threshold">
                     <EventOut port="out" />
                     <Transition regime="refr" />
                 </OnCondition>

             </Regime>
         </Dynamics>

     </ComponentType>
</xcode>
 </p>
 
 <p>
 Once this definition is available, a particular model using this structure can be specified with the following 
 XML: 
 <xcode>
    <refractiaf threshold="-40mV" refractoryPeriod="5ms" capacitance="1nF"
               vleak = "-80mV" gleak="100pS" vreset="-70mV" v0="-70mV" deltaV="10mV"/>
 </xcode>
 </p>

<p>
    More complex models will have nested components and other types of parameters, but the basic principle of 
    separating out the equations and parameters for reusable model components, such that the equations are 
    only stated once, remains the same.
</p>

<p>
    
</p>

</page>